http://www.britishtriathlon.org/about-us/governance/privacy-notice

By continuing to use this website you agree to our cookie policy. Close
About Us
Privacy Notice
Cookie Information
Join
Club member? Get a discount when you join.
Membership of British Triathlon has a wide range of benefits including:
Privacy Notice
This privacy notice tells you what to expect when British Triathlon processes your personal information
How we use your information
The British Triathlon Federation and is the National Governing Body for Triathlon, Aquathlon and Duathlon.
British Triathlon will be a "controller" of the personal information that you provide to us through this website, unless otherwise stated.
This privacy notice applies to information British Triathlon collects about:
Members of Triathlon England, Welsh Triathlon or Triathlon Scotland
Day Member of Triathlon England, Welsh Triathlon or Triathlon Scotland
Annual Awards Nominations
We’ve created a child friendly version of our privacy policy, for anyone aged 16 and under, to help you understand how we use your data.
Child Friendly Privacy Policy
Major Event Privacy Policy
This Policy describes how we use your personal data when you enter either or both of (i) the ‘ITU World Triathlon Leeds’ or (ii) the ‘ITU World Triathlon Mixed Relay, Nottingham’ events to be held in 2019 including the mass participation races.
Major Events Privacy Policy British Triathlon Pop Up Marketing 2019 Policy
Volunteer Privacy Policy
This Policy describes how we use your personal data when you interact with British Triathlon as a Volunteer.
Volunteer Privacy Policy
Jump to the section on your rights and how to contact us.
Members of Triathlon England, Welsh Triathlon or Triathlon Scotland
As a member of Triathlon England, Welsh Triathlon or Triathlon Scotland we process personal information including:
personal details - such as name, title, address, email addresses, telephone numbers, date of birth, gender, account passwords
participation details - for example club;
equality information - disability (if any), ethnic group, religious belief; gender identity and sexual orientation;
payment details - credit/debit card details (which we do not retain) and other payment details such as bank account number, sort code, card details so we can receive payments from you and details of the financial transactions with you;
membership photo - the photo used on your membership card
marketing communication preferences - so that we know whether and how we should contact you.
records of your interactions with us such as telephone conversations, emails and other correspondence and your instructions to us;
records of your attendance at any events or competitions hosted by us or by permitted event organisers;
How we collect personal data
We may collect your personal information in a number of ways, principally:
Directly from you, for example when you apply for British Triathlon Membership, purchase or use our products or services including tickets, merchandise, ClubSpark, attend BTF events, enter a competition, join a performance programme as an athlete, provide coaching or officiating services, and make enquiries on our website, and when you interact with us during your participation in British Triathlon in various other ways;
From someone else acting on your behalf, for example when a parent or guardian has purchased British Triathlon Membership for you as their child, or if another purchases a membership as a gift, or when British Triathlon staff who are working with you in your capacity as a participant, coach or official record information about you, for example when coordinating competitions;
On rare occasions, we may receive information about you from others who are not acting on your behalf (for example, where someone makes a complaint about you which we then investigate);
By creating it ourselves, for example when we produce race reports from watching participants compete at events; and/or
When you make enquiries on our website, or when you interact with us (for example, where you volunteer to assist with a competition, event or league organised by us, sign up for our volunteer communications, enquire about a volunteering opportunity), or through the club annual registration process and when your details are passed to us for the purposes of volunteer recognition.
Why we need your personal information - contractual purposes
We need to process our members’ personal information so that we can manage your membership. We will use our members’ personal information to:
provide you with core member services, including, insurance, licensing, voting, membership cards;
set up your online membership account and administer your account online;
send you membership communications by post or email in relation to essential membership services, including but not limited to, general meeting notices, membership renewals, membership fees’ information and information on membership benefits;
If you do not provide us with all of the personal information that we need to collect then this may affect our ability to offer the above membership services and benefits.
Why we need your personal information - legitimate interests
We also process our members’ personal information in pursuit of our legitimate interests to:
monitor and develop participation in the sport of Triathlon by monitoring members’ engagement and participation through events and membership and inviting our members to participate in surveys for researching and development purposes;
use our members’ personal information relating to your disability (if any), ethnic group, religious belief, gender identity and sexual orientation for equality monitoring purposes as required by Sport England. We will process such personal information through aggregated and anonymised reports to identify and keep under review the existence or absence of equality of opportunity or treatment between groups of people within the same categories to promote or maintain equality within our sport;
deliver film and photography. Our competitions and events may be filmed for live streaming purposes and your personal information may also be used in images captured from our competitions and events, which we use for promotional, education and development purposes;
invite our members as award winners or guests to our awards ceremony which includes asking our clubs to nominate individuals for awards and shortlisting such individuals to select the winners, who we will then contact by email;
respond to and communicate with members regarding your questions, comments, support needs or complaints, concerns or allegations in relation to the sport of Triathlon. Complaints will be dealt with in line with the Triathlon England complaints process.  We will use your personal information to investigate your complaint, to suspend membership, take disciplinary action;
Where we process your personal information in pursuit of our legitimate interests, you have the right to object to us using your personal information for the above purposes. If you wish to object to any of the above processing, please contact us on dataprotection@britishtriathlon.org.  If we agree and comply with your objection, this may affect our ability to undertake the tasks above for the benefit of you as a member.
Why we need your personal information - legal obligations
We are under a legal obligation to process certain personal information relating to our members for the purposes of complying with our obligations under:
the Companies Act 2006, to maintain a register of our members, which includes our members’ name, address, the date they were admitted to membership and the date on which they ceased to be our member, and hold general meetings, including issuing notices and voting arrangements;
the Equality Act 2010, which requires us to process personal information to make reasonable adjustments where necessary.
Why we need your personal information - consent
We use consent as the legal basis to:
send out marketing communications to promote and encourage participation in the sport of Triathlon which include monthly newsletters, event promotions and offers from official sponsors and partners;
pass your details onto the Triathlon Trust - only if you have donated and consented to this
we have made the decision not to send any marketing communications to any junior members under the age of 16. This is because, by law, people under the age of 16 are not recognised as being able to fully understand why they are agreeing to or opting in to something. We will only communicate with any junior members under the age of 16 if they have applied to race in one of our British Triathlon organised events including but not limited to Youth and Junior Super Series events and will need to receive information on this event (such as whether they have been selected to participate or not), or if it directly relates to essential membership services as stated in ‘Why we need your personal information – contractual purposes’.
Who we share your personal information with
Personal information is shared with Welsh Triathlon and Triathlon Scotland in order to help them administer their membership services. Have a look at the Welsh Triathlon privacy notice and the Triathlon Scotland privacy notice.
If your personal information is included in any images or videos taken by us at our competitions and events, we may share this with Sport England for promotional and/or journalistic purposes.
We may be required to share personal information with statutory or regulatory authorities and organisations to comply with statutory obligations. Such organisations include the Health & Safety Executive, Disclosure & Barring Service, and UK Police and law enforcement agencies for the purposes of prevention and detection of crime.
We may also share personal information with our professional and legal advisors for the purposes of taking advice.
British Triathlon may share personal information with companies who help with membership fulfillment. For example British Triathlon currently employs Synergy Print to provide the printing and distribution of membership cards.
Limited information (name and membership number) may be shared with individual clubs if you have indicated that you are a member of that club.
We may pass limited details on to help determine if event competitors are members or not. For example with Triathlon England Championship events or to Regional Committees to help with the running of local league series. This is only so that it can be determined from event results who is a member.
Your data may be shared with data processors to help with communication delivery. For example, we use a third party provider, MailChimp, to deliver some of our email communications which might include e-newsletters and direct marketing emails. Your data may be shared when we may use data processors to conduct online surveys (for example SurveyMonkey) so that we can report on trends and gain feedback; or with companies who provide cloud-based file storage and sharing like Dropbox and Sharepoint.
We will pass some personal data on to our payment providers in order to take payment for your membership. This generally includes payment details along with name, address and contact details which are sometimes used in fraud prevention.
If you have donated to the Triathlon Trust during the membership purchasing process and consented to your details being passed on, we will pass your name and contact details on to the Triathlon Trust.
If we do share personal information with external third parties, we will only share such personal information strictly required for the specific purposes and take reasonable steps to ensure that recipients shall only process the disclosed personal information in accordance with those purposes.
How long we keep your personal information
We will only keep your personal information for as long as necessary to provide you with membership services. Unless you ask us not to, we will review and possibly delete your personal information where you have not renewed your membership with us for six years.
We will keep certain personal information of members for longer in order to confirm your identity, when you were a member of Triathlon England and for how long. We need to do this to comply with the Companies Act 2006, which requires us to keep a register of members or in the event of a claim against British Triathlon.
Transferral of personal data outside the European Union
Your personal data may be transferred outside of the EU when using third party services such as Dropbox, MailChimp or SurveyMonkey. Whenever your data is transferred outside the EU we will make sure the organisation receiving the personal data has provided adequate safeguards. For example, Dropbox and MailChimp participate in and has certified their compliance with the EU-U.S. Privacy Shield Framework and the Swiss-U.S Privacy Shield Framework.
Jump to the section on your rights and how to contact us.
Day Member of Triathlon England, Welsh Triathlon or Triathlon Scotland
As a day member of Triathlon England, Welsh Triathlon or Triathlon Scotland registering for a race licence we process personal information including:
personal details - such as name, email addresses, date of birth, gender
payment details - credit/debit card details (which we do not retain)
marketing communication preferences - so that we know whether and how we should contact you.
records of your interactions with us such as telephone conversations, emails and other correspondence and your instructions to us;
records of your attendance at any events or competitions hosted by us or by permitted event organisers;
How we collect personal data
We may collect your personal information in a number of ways, principally:
Directly from you, for example when you apply for British Triathlon Membership, purchase or use our products or services including tickets, merchandise, ClubSpark, attend BTF events, enter a competition, join a performance programme as an athlete, provide coaching or officiating services, and make enquiries on our website, and when you interact with us during your participation in British Triathlon in various other ways;
From someone else acting on your behalf, for example when a parent or guardian has purchased British Triathlon Membership for you as their child, or if another purchases a membership as a gift, or when British Triathlon staff who are working with you in your capacity as a participant, coach or official record information about you, for example when coordinating competitions;
On rare occasions, we may receive information about you from others who are not acting on your behalf (for example, where someone makes a complaint about you which we then investigate);
By creating it ourselves, for example when we produce race reports from watching participants compete at events; and/or
When you make enquiries on our website, or when you interact with us (for example, where you volunteer to assist with a competition, event or league organised by us, sign up for our volunteer communications, enquire about a volunteering opportunity), or through the club annual registration process and when your details are passed to us for the purposes of volunteer recognition.
Why we need your personal information - contractual purposes
We need to process our day members’ personal information so that we can manage your membership. We will use our day members’ personal information to:
provide you with day member services, including, insurance, licensing;
send you day membership communications by email in relation to essential day membership services, including but not limited to, insurance, licensing;
If you do not provide us with all of the personal information that we need to collect then this may affect our ability to offer the above day membership services.
Why we need your personal information - legitimate interests
We also process our day members’ personal information in pursuit of our legitimate interests to:
monitor and develop participation in the sport of Triathlon by monitoring day members’ engagement and participation through events and membership and inviting our day members to participate in surveys for researching and development purposes;
deliver film and photography. Our competitions and events may be filmed for live streaming purposes and your personal information may also be used in images captured from our competitions and events, which we use for promotional, education and development purposes;
respond to and communicate with day members regarding your questions, comments, support needs or complaints, concerns or allegations in relation to the sport of Triathlon. Complaints will be dealt with in line with the Triathlon England complaints process.  We will use your personal information to investigate your complaint, take disciplinary action;
To use the data to comply with the terms of the day members’ insurance policy and the handing of claims;
Where we process your personal information in pursuit of our legitimate interests, you have the right to object to us using your personal information for the above purposes. If you wish to object to any of the above processing, please contact us on dataprotection@britishtriathlon.org.  If we agree and comply with your objection, this may affect our ability to undertake the tasks above for the benefit of you as a day member.
Why we need your personal information - legal obligations
We are under a legal obligation to process certain personal information relating to our day members for the purposes of complying with our obligations under:
the Equality Act 2010, which requires us to process personal information to make reasonable adjustments where necessary.
Why we need your personal information - consent
We use consent as the legal basis to:
send out marketing communications to promote and encourage participation in the sport of Triathlon which include monthly newsletters, event promotions and offers from official sponsors and partners;
we have made the decision not to send any marketing communications to any junior day members under the age of 16. This is because, by law, people under the age of 16 are not recognised as being able to fully understand why they are agreeing to or opting in to something. We will only communicate with any junior day members under the age of 16 if they have applied to race in one of our British Triathlon organised events including but not limited to Youth and Junior Super Series events and will need to receive information on this event (such as whether they have been selected to participate or not), or if it directly relates to essential day membership services as stated in ‘Why we need your personal information – contractual purposes’.
Who we share your personal information with
Personal information is shared with Welsh Triathlon and Triathlon Scotland in order to help them administer their day membership services. Have a look at the Welsh Triathlon privacy notice and the Triathlon Scotland privacy notice.
If your personal information is included in any images or videos taken by us at our competitions and events, we may share this with Sport England for promotional and/or journalistic purposes.
We may be required to share personal information with statutory or regulatory authorities and organisations to comply with statutory obligations. Such organisations include the Health & Safety Executive, Disclosure & Barring Service, and UK Police and law enforcement agencies for the purposes of prevention and detection of crime.
We may also share personal information with our professional and legal advisors for the purposes of taking advice.
Limited information (name and membership number) may be shared with individual clubs if you have indicated that you are a member of that club.
We may pass limited details on to help determine if event competitors are members or not. For example with Triathlon England Championship events or to Regional Committees to help with the running of local league series. This is only so that it can be determined from event results who is a member.
Your data may be shared with data processors to help with communication delivery. For example, we use a third party provider, MailChimp, to deliver some of our email communications which might include e-newsletters and direct marketing emails. Your data may be shared when we may use data processors to conduct online surveys (for example SurveyMonkey) so that we can report on trends and gain feedback; or with companies who provide cloud-based file storage and sharing like Dropbox and Sharepoint.
We will pass some personal data on to our payment providers in order to take payment for your day membership. This generally includes payment details along with name and card holder details which are sometimes used in fraud prevention.
If we do share personal information with external third parties, we will only share such personal information strictly required for the specific purposes and take reasonable steps to ensure that recipients shall only process the disclosed personal information in accordance with those purposes.
How long we keep your personal information
We will only keep your personal information for as long as necessary to provide you with day membership services. Unless you ask us not to, we will review and possibly delete your personal information where you have not renewed your membership with us for six years.
We will keep certain personal information of day members for longer in order to confirm your identity, when you were a member of Triathlon England and for how long. We need to do this to comply with our insurance provider in the event of a claim against British Triathlon.
Transferral of personal data outside the European Union
Your personal data may be transferred outside of the EU when using third party services such as Dropbox, MailChimp or SurveyMonkey. Whenever your data is transferred outside the EU we will make sure the organisation receiving the personal data has provided adequate safeguards. For example, Dropbox and MailChimp participate in and has certified their compliance with the EU-U.S. Privacy Shield Framework and the Swiss-U.S Privacy Shield Framework.
Jump to the section on your rights and how to contact us.
People entering an event via our online entry system
British Triathlon is the “Co-controller” and “processor” of the personal information that you provide to us, unless otherwise stated.
Your permitted Event Organiser of the specific event you are entering is the “Co-controller” of the personal information that you provide to us, unless otherwise stated.
Throughout this section of the privacy notice the term “We” refers to British Triathlon and/or your permitted Event Organiser of the specific event you are entering.
When you enter an event via our online entry system we process certain personal information including:
personal details – name, address, email address, and date of birth;
membership details (if applicable);
payment details  (which we do not);
participation details – club, team name;
emergency contact details – name, contact number, relationship;
relevant medical information (if any);
equality information – disability (if any), ethnic group, religious belief, gender identity and sexual orientation;
experience levels, behaviour and interests – optional research questions for monitoring purposes; and
any additional information needed for the event - for example swim times, t-shirt size;
Why we need your personal information - contractual purposes
We need to collect our event participants’ personal information so that we can manage your event entry and participation in the event. We will use our event participants’ personal information to:
provide you with core event services and opportunities including but not limited to, entering you into the event, selecting your age category, adding you to the start list and including you in the results and potential prizes;
send you event related communications by post, email, text or telephone including but not limited to; confirming your entry, issuing pre-race information and distributing your result; and
any other contractual requirements specific to the event.
If you do not provide us with all of the personal information that we need to collect then this may affect our ability to offer the above services.
Why we need your personal information – legitimate purposes
We also process our event participants’ personal information in pursuit of our legitimate interests to:
promote and encourage participation in the sport of Triathlon by sending other potential participants communications and booking information for upcoming competitions and events. Our competitions and events may be filmed for live streaming purposes and your personal information may also be used in images and footage captured from our competitions and events, which we use for promotional, education, commercial and development purposes;
monitor and develop participation in the sport of Triathlon by monitoring engagement and participation through events and membership and inviting our participants to participate in surveys for researching and development purposes;
respond to and communicate with participants regarding your questions, comments, support needs or complaints, concerns or allegations in relation to the sport of Triathlon. Complaints will be dealt with in line with the relevant complaints process. We will use your personal information to investigate your complaint, take disciplinary action;
use our over event participants’ personal information relating to your disability (if any), ethnic group, religious belief, gender identity and sexual orientation for equality monitoring purposes as required by Sport England. We will process such personal information through aggregated and anonymised reports to identify and keep under review the existence or absence of equality of opportunity or treatment between groups of people within the same categories to promote or maintain equality within our sport. This individual information is not shared with your permitted Event Organiser
Where we process your personal information in pursuit of our legitimate interests, you have the right to object to us using your personal information for the above purposes. If you wish to object to any of the above processing, please contact us on dataprotection@britishtriathlon.org. If we agree and comply with your objection, this may affect our ability to undertake the tasks above for the benefit of you as a major event participant.
Why we need your personal information – vital interests
We need contact details of someone we can contact in an emergency if a situation occurs where we are concerned for your welfare this includes but is not limited to, we are unable to locate you, you are involved in an incident and/or accident where you have injured yourself and/or you are involved in an incident and/or accident where you are unconscious. Before sharing someone else’s personal information to be used as your emergency contact, you must gain their permission to do so. Their personal information will be secured securely as per this privacy notice.
We need your medical details in case you are involved in an incident and/or accident where you are not able to communicate with the first aid responders and/or emergency services. Your medical details will be shared with the first aid responders and/or emergency services should you be involved in an incident and/or accident.
Who we share your personal information with
We will pass some personal data on to our payment providers in order to take payment for your club affiliation. This generally includes payment details along with name, address and contact details which are sometimes used in fraud prevention.
In order to deliver the event service, your race entry and results will be publicly available both online and in print format. These will include your name, age category, gender and club/team name. Where we electronically time events, we will share your personal details with our timing companies so your time can be recorded and added to the results.
If your personal information is included in any images or footage taken by us at our competitions and events, we may use these and share these with Sport England and our official partners and sponsors for promotional and/or journalistic purposes.
We may also share your personal information with our official partners and sponsors for marketing purposes where you consented for us to do so.
We may be required to share personal information with statutory or regulatory authorities and organisations to comply with statutory obligations. Such organisations include the Health & Safety Executive, the Emergency Services, the Safeguarding Board and UK Police and law enforcement agencies for the purposes of safeguarding children, managing major incidents/accidents and your welfare.
We may also share personal information with our professional and legal advisors for the purposes of taking advice.
Your data may be shared with data processors to help with communication delivery. For example, we use a third party provider, MailChimp, to deliver some of our email communications.
If we do share personal information with external third parties, we will only share such personal information strictly required for the specific purposes and take reasonable steps to ensure that recipients shall only process the disclosed personal information in accordance with those purposes.
How long we keep your personal information
We will only keep your personal information for as long as necessary to provide you with relevant triathlon services. Unless you ask us not to, we will review and possibly delete your personal information where you have not participated in any events with us for six years.
British Triathlon will keep certain personal information of British Triathlon members for longer in order to confirm your identity, whether you were a member of British Triathlon and for how long. We need to do this to comply with the Companies Act 2006, which requires us to keep a register of members.
We will also keep certain personal information for longer in the event of a claim against British Triathlon or your permitted Event Organiser.
Transferral of personal data outside the European Union
Your personal data may be transferred outside of the EU when using third party services such as MailChimp which we use to help with club communications.
Whenever your data is transferred outside the EU we will make sure the organisation receiving the personal data has provided adequate safeguards.
Jump to the section on your rights and how to contact us.
People entering a course via our course booking system
When you enter a course via our course booking system, we process certain personal information which might include:
your personal membership details - such as name, address, email address, telephone number, date of birth, gender, club, membership number
if you are not already a Triathlon England, Triathlon Scotland or Welsh Triathlon member, we will ask for extra information around disability (if any), ethnic group, religious belief, gender identity and sexual orientation
payment details (which we do not retain)
supporting evidence to strengthen an application
extra details relevant to the course you are booking on to, for example, motorcycle officiating details, kit sizes, mentor experience, coaching level 2 direct entry supporting evidence
Why we need your personal information - contractual purposes
In order for us to provide the course entry you have requested and to meet our committments to you, we will have to process the details you submitted.
We might use your personal information to:
take payment and send payment confirmation emails;
make refunds when necessary;
generate and administer course register lists, for example, so we can transfer people from on course to another or so we know who is attending on the day;
send important communications related to the course you have booked on to;
approve or reject submissions where relevant (for example Coaching Level 2 Direct Entry);
Why we need your personal information - legitimate interests
We might also use your personal information in pursuit of our interests which include:
aggregate reporting on trends and the numbers and demographics of people attending courses
use our information relating to your disability (if any), ethnic group, religious belief, gender identity and sexual orientation for equality monitoring purposes as required by Sport England. We will process such personal information through aggregated and anonymised reports to identify and keep under review the existence or absence of equality of opportunity or treatment between groups of people within the same categories to promote or maintain equality within our sport
Where we process your personal information in pursuit of our legitimate interests, you have the right to object to us using your personal information for the above purposes. If you wish to object to any of the above processing, please contact us on dataprotection@britishtriathlon.org. If we agree and comply with your objection, this may affect our ability to undertake the tasks above.
Who we share your personal information with
Some of your personal information might be shared with third parties who help with the delivery of the course you have booked on to. For example so they know who will be turning up on the day, if anyone has any medical issues that need to be catered for or for other administrative tasks.
We will pass some personal data on to our payment providers in order to take payment for your registration or entry. This generally includes payment details along with name, address and contact details which are sometimes used in fraud prevention.
Your data may be shared with data processors to help with communication delivery. For example, we use a third party provider, MailChimp, to deliver some of our email communications.
If you are entering a Coaching Level 2 Direct Entry course your personal and application details will be passed on to the tutor responsible for accepting applicants.
If we do share personal information with external third parties, we will only share such personal information strictly required for the specific purposes and take reasonable steps to ensure that recipients shall only process the disclosed personal information in accordance with those purposes.
How long we keep your personal information
A lot of the personal information used in the course booking process is tied into your membership information so you should see the membership section of this privacy notice to see those retention periods.
The course booking specific information will be retained for at least 5 years or until British Triathlon no longer needs it.
Transferral of personal data outside the European Union
Your personal data may be transferred outside of the EU when using third party services such as MailChimp which we use to help with communications or file-storage and sharing services like Dropbox.
Whenever your data is transferred outside the EU we will make sure the organisation receiving the personal data has provided adequate safeguards.
Jump to the section on your rights and how to contact us.
People entering an Age-Group event
When you enter an Age-Group event we process certain personal information including:
your personal membership details - such as name, address, email address, telephone number, date of birth, gender
results from qualifying event (if applicable)
supporting evidence to strengthen your application
emergency contact details
any medical conditions the organisers should be aware of
payment details (which we do not retain)
Why we need your personal information - contractual purposes
In order for us to provide the Age-Group registration or entry you have requested and to meet our committments to you, we will have to process the details you submitted.
We might use your personal information to:
take payment and send payment confirmation emails;
make refunds when necessary;
help select Age-Group teams;
send communication updates which might include team confirmations or important information required for your event;
enter qualified athletes into events;
provide team managers with emergency contact information and important medical details they need to be aware of when at the event;
Why we need your personal information - legitimate interests
We might also use your personal information in pursuit of our interests which include:
aggregate reporting on trends and the numbers and demographics of Age-Group athletes
sending communications specifically relevant to the Age-Group community, for example updates about Age-Group kit
Who we share your personal information with
Your personal information is shared with our volunteer Age-Group team managers to help with the administration of the Age-Group process and when accompanying athletes to events.
We will pass some personal data on to our payment providers in order to take payment for your registration or entry. This generally includes payment details along with name, address and contact details which are sometimes used in fraud prevention.
If you are selected to compete for the Age-Group team, your personal data is likely to be shared with the respective event organiser in order to enter you into the event.
Your data may be shared with data processors to help with communication delivery. For example, we use a third party provider, MailChimp, to deliver some of our email communications to Age-Groupers.
If we do share personal information with external third parties, we will only share such personal information strictly required for the specific purposes and take reasonable steps to ensure that recipients shall only process the disclosed personal information in accordance with those purposes.
How long we keep your personal information
A lot of the personal information used in the Age-Group process is tied into your membership information so you should see the membership section of this privacy notice to see those retention periods.
The Age-Group registration and entry specific information will be retained for at least 5 years or until British Triathlon no longer needs it.
Transferral of personal data outside the European Union
Your personal data may be transferred outside of the EU when using third party services such as MailChimp which we use to help with Age-Group communications or file-storage and sharing services like Dropbox.
It may also be neccessary for your personal information to be sent to event organisers outside of the EU in order to enter you into a specific event.
Whenever your data is transferred outside the EU we will make sure the organisation receiving the personal data has provided adequate safeguards.
Jump to the section on your rights and how to contact us.
Clubs affiliating via the British Triathlon website
When a club affiliates via the British Triathlon website, a lot of the information submitted is not "personal information" because it relates to the club rather than relating to an identifiable person. However, we do process certain personal information including:
the personal details of the club primary contact - such as name, address, email address, telephone number, date of birth, gender
payment details (which we do not retain) which might be personal information
the name, email and membership number of the club welfare contact
if applicable, the names, emails and membership numbers of the club chairperson, secretary and treasurer
How we collect personal data
We may collect your personal information in a number of ways, principally:
Directly from you, for example when you apply for British Triathlon Membership or Affiliation, purchase or use our products or services including tickets, merchandise, ClubSpark, attend BTF events, enter a competition, join a performance programme as an athlete, provide coaching or officiating services, and make enquiries on our website, and when you interact with us during your participation in British Triathlon in various other ways;
From someone else acting on your behalf, for example when a parent or guardian has purchased British Triathlon Membership for you as their child, or if another purchases a membership as a gift, or when British Triathlon staff who are working with you in your capacity as a participant, coach or official record information about you, for example when coordinating competitions;
On rare occasions, we may receive information about you from others who are not acting on your behalf (for example, where someone makes a complaint about you which we then investigate);
By creating it ourselves, for example when we produce race reports from watching participants compete at events; and/or
When you make enquiries on our website, or when you interact with us (for example, where you volunteer to assist with a competition, event or league organised by us, sign up for our volunteer communications, enquire about a volunteering opportunity), or through the club annual registration process and when your details are passed to us for the purposes of volunteer recognition.
Why we need your personal information - contractual purposes
In order for us to provide the club affiliation service you have requested and to meet our committments to you, we will have to process the details you submitted.
We might use your personal information to:
take payment and send payment confirmation emails;
make refunds when necessary;
contact you or the club contacts with important service-based communications related to your club's affiliation. For example, questions from our membership team who deal with club affiliation; renewal reminders; updates if there are changes to club affiliation, rules and regulations or any technicaly aspects of the sport clubs need to be aware of; important communications about club welfare; contact from our regional managers to help with our club support in terms of club development, funding, accreditation, club coaching;
Who we share your personal information with
Personal information is shared with Welsh Triathlon in order to help them administer their club affiliation services.
We will pass some personal data on to our payment providers in order to take payment for your club affiliation. This generally includes payment details along with name, address and contact details which are sometimes used in fraud prevention.
If we do share personal information with external third parties, we will only share such personal information strictly required for the specific purposes and take reasonable steps to ensure that recipients shall only process the disclosed personal information in accordance with those purposes.
How long we keep your personal information
As a club primary contact, a lot of the personal information processed is tied into your membership information so you should see the membership section of this privacy notice to see those retention periods.
The club specific information (welfare, chairperson, secretary and treasurer contact details) will be retained for at least 5 years after a club ceases affiliating or until British Triathlon no longer needs it.
Transferral of personal data outside the European Union
Your personal data may be transferred outside of the EU when using third party services such as MailChimp which we use to help with club communications.
Whenever your data is transferred outside the EU we will make sure the organisation receiving the personal data has provided adequate safeguards.
Jump to the section on your rights and how to contact us.
British Triathlon coaches
As a British Triathlon coach, you should also view the membership and course booking sections of this privacy notice to see the how much of your personal data is processed. In addition, we process certain personal information including:
personal details – name, address, email address, and date of birth, club, membership number
course finder details (if applicable) which include your public contact email address, address (so people can look up by postcode searches), biography, social media accounts, the services, distances and abilities you offer or cater for
notes or records of your interactions with us such as telephone conversations, emails and other correspondence and your instructions to us;
On the Learning Hub e-learning website (if applicable):
contact details – name, address, email address, and date of birth
passwords
dates & times the system was accessed
IP address
what actions took place (e.g sections viewed/ tasks completed)
submission of course work
photo (if added)
completion and sign off of course work
personal profile and medical questionnaire
certificates of completion
Why we need your personal information - contractual purposes
We need to process your personal information so that we can manage a number of processes for coaching. We might use your personal information for:
registration for and administration of the Learning Hub
registration with Awarding Body
record of completing a coaching course against your membership record
completion of course content via the Learning Hub
ensuring your safety and support on courses (medical information & learner profile)
sending you important service-based communications related to your role as a coach
Why we need your personal information - legitimate interests
We might also use your personal information in pursuit of our interests which include:
aggregate reporting on trends and the numbers and demographics of coaches
develop and maintain qualifications, including sending email communications to members to inform you of upcoming courses, renewal requirements and verify that you have completed any mandatory training and PVG/ DBS child protection requirements.
respond to and communicate with coaches regarding your questions, comments, support needs or complaints, concerns or allegations in relation to the sport of Triathlon. Complaints will be dealt with in line with the British Triathlon’s complaints procedures. We will use your personal information to investigate your complaint, to suspend membership, take disciplinary action;
help maintain the security and performance of our website & Learning Hub
as part of our 1st4sport recognised centre status to deliver UKCC approved qualifications
using coaches’ personal information relating to your disability (if any), ethnic group, religious belief, gender identity and sexual orientation for equality monitoring purposes as required by Sport England. We will process such personal information through aggregated and anonymised reports to identify and keep under review the existence or absence of equality of opportunity or treatment between groups of people within the same categories to promote or maintain equality within our sport;
Where we process your personal information in pursuit of our legitimate interests, you have the right to object to us using your personal information for the above purposes. If you wish to object to any of the above processing, please contact us on dataprotection@britishtriathlon.org.  If we agree and comply with your objection, this may affect our ability to undertake the tasks above for the benefit of you as a coach.
Who we share your personal information with
We may be required to share personal information with statutory or regulatory authorities and organisations to comply with statutory obligations. Such organisations include the Health & Safety Executive, Disclosure & Barring Service (DBS), and UK Police and law enforcement agencies for the purposes of safeguarding children.
We may also share personal information with our professional and legal advisors for the purposes of taking advice.
We share coach education learner details with 1st4sport as our awarding body, this includes name, address, date of birth and gender.
We share learner details with course tutors for contacting learners and maintaining records, this includes name, address, date of birth, gender, phone number. Additionally, learners will share medical information with the tutors on courses where physical activity is required. We have strict guidelines that our tutors must follow when handling learners personal data, which includes distribution and deletion.
We share personal details with third parties who help with the running and administration of the Learning Hub website.
If we do share personal information with external third parties, we will only share such personal information strictly required for the specific purposes and take reasonable steps to ensure that recipients shall only process the disclosed personal information in accordance with those purposes.
How long we keep your personal information
A lot of the personal information processed as a coach is tied into your membership information so you should see the membership section of this privacy notice to see those retention periods.
We will only keep your coaching personal information for as long as necessary to provide you with coaching services.
Transferral of personal data outside the European Union
Your personal data may be transferred outside of the EU when using third party services such as MailChimp which we use to help with coach communications or file-storage and sharing services like Dropbox.
Whenever your data is transferred outside the EU we will make sure the organisation receiving the personal data has provided adequate safeguards.
Jump to the section on your rights and how to contact us.
British Triathlon Technical Officials
As a British Triathlon technical official, you should also view the membership and course booking sections of this privacy notice to see the how much of your personal data is processed. In addition, we process certain personal information including:
your personal membership details - such as name, address, email address, telephone number, date of birth, gender
specific Technical Official details such as preferred travel distance, clothing sizes and the regions in which you officiate
motorcycle officiating details (if applicable) which include driving licence number, motocycle bike specifications and external qualifications you hold
your consent choices to receive specific Technical Official-related communications
any special requirements that need to be catered for when you officiate at an event
Why we need your personal information - contractual purposes
In order for us to run the officiating programme, we will have to process the personal information you have provided.
We might use your personal information to:
help with the process of assigning Technical Officials to events;
allow submitting of event and shadow reports
administer qualification records;
send important communication updates, for example about events your have expressed your interest to officiate in and been assigned a role to;
Why we need your personal information - legitimate interests
We might also use your personal information in pursuit of our interests which include:
aggregate reporting on trends and the numbers and demographics of Technical Officials
sending communications specifically relevant in your role as a Technical Official
Where we process your personal information in pursuit of our legitimate interests, you have the right to object to us using your personal information for the above purposes. If you wish to object to any of the above processing, please contact us on dataprotection@britishtriathlon.org.  If we agree and comply with your objection, this may affect our ability to undertake the tasks above for the benefit of you as a Technical Official.
Why we need your personal information - consent
We use consent as the legal basis to:
send out email round-ups with the latest activity in your region or reminder emails about the events you are due to officiate in.
You are always able to remove your consent to these within the 'My Personal Details' section of the Officials Management System.
Who we share your personal information with
Limited personal information is shared with our volunteer Regional Officials Coordinators and Technical Committee to help with the administration of the Officials Management System. Your name, email address, phone number, town, county, region and qualification level is shared with them along with any special requirements that you provide when you register to officiate at an event.
Limited personal information is shared with other members of the officiating team to which you have been appointed. The name, email address and phone number is shared between all Technical Officials appointed to the officiating team only. This also includes the Technical Delegates of ITU/ETU events held in Great Britain, where you have been appointed to the officiating team.
Limited personal information is shared with the Event Organiser of any events where you are assigned as the Chief Technical Official or a member of the officiating team. The name and email address of the Chief Technical Official is shared with the Event Organiser; the name(s) of all members of the officiating team are shared with the Event Organiser.
Limited personal information is shared with the International Triathlon Union (ITU) in the event of attending an ITU Technical Official course. Your name, email address and date of birth is shared with them.
Your data may be shared with data processors to help with communication delivery. For example, we use a third party provider, MailChimp, to deliver some of our email communications to Technical Officials.
If we do share personal information with external third parties, we will only share such personal information strictly required for the specific purposes and take reasonable steps to ensure that recipients shall only process the disclosed personal information in accordance with those purposes.
How long we keep your personal information
A lot of the personal information processed as a Technical Official is tied into your membership information so you should see the membership section of this privacy notice to see those retention periods.
Your specific Technical Official information will be retained for at least 5 years or until British Triathlon no longer needs it.
Transferral of personal data outside the European Union
Your personal data may be transferred outside of the EU when using third party services such as MailChimp which we use to help with officials communications or file-storage and sharing services like Dropbox.
Whenever your data is transferred outside the EU we will make sure the organisation receiving the personal data has provided adequate safeguards.
Jump to the section on your rights and how to contact us.
Event Results
In publishling event results on our website, we process certain personal information which might include:
personal details - name, gender, age group, date of birth, membership number, club (depending on what we receive from Event Organisers)
performance details (times and positions)
Why we need your personal information - legitimate interests
We might also use your personal information in pursuit of our interests which include:
aggregate reporting on participation trends and the numbers and demographics of people competing in triathlon
archiving results to provide people with a history of events competed in and to allow for historical research
Where we process your personal information in pursuit of our legitimate interests, you have the right to object to us using your personal information for the above purposes. If you wish to object to any of the above processing, please contact us on dataprotection@britishtriathlon.org. If we agree and comply with your objection, this may affect our ability to undertake the tasks above.
Who we share your personal information with
Some of your personal information is shared publically on your athlete page: your name and the record of your event results are always shown. In addition, your gender, age group, club, region and membership photo can be shared publically depending on your privacy settings. To remove any of this personal information from public view, please go to your My Account.
Some of your personal information is also shared publically on our results pages. What is displayed depends on what information event organisers have provided us, it can include: position, name, gender, age group, club and overall time and individual stage times.
How long we keep your personal information
Result data is intended to be kept indefinitely as a historic record or until British Triathlon no longer needs it.
Transferral of personal data outside the European Union
We do not currently transfer event results data outside of the European Union.
Jump to the section on your rights and how to contact us.
OpenActive API
People who use our OpenActive API or have opted in to our OpenActive mailing list provide us with their email address.
Why we need your personal information - legitimate interests
British Triathlon processes the IP addresses of visitors of our OpenActive API to help maintain the security and performance of the service.
Where we process your personal information in pursuit of our legitimate interests, you have the right to object to us using your personal information for the above purposes. If you wish to object to any of the above processing, please contact us on dataprotection@britishtriathlon.org.  If we agree and comply with your objection, this may affect our ability to use the API.
Why we need your personal information - consent
We use consent as the legal basis to:
send out emails with updates concerning our OpenActive APIs.
You are always able to remove your consent by clicking the unsubscribe link at the bottom of any email sent out or by contacting us at dataprotection@britishtriathlon.org.
Who we share your personal information with
Your data may be shared with data processors such as Mailchimp to help with communication delivery.
How long we keep your personal information
Your email address will be retained until we no longer offer the OpenActive mailing list.
Transferral of personal data outside the European Union
Your personal data may be transferred outside of the EU when using third party services such as MailChimp which we use to help with communications.
Whenever your data is transferred outside the EU we will make sure the organisation receiving the personal data has provided adequate safeguards.
Jump to the section on your rights and how to contact us.
ClubSpark API
People who use our ClubSpark integration (API) or have opted in to use ClubSpark provide us with their first name, last name, email address, gender, phone no,  DOB, and address.
Why we need your personal information - legitimate interests
British Triathlon processes the IP addresses of visitors of our ClubSpark API to help maintain the security and performance of the service.
Where we process your personal information in pursuit of our legitimate interests, you have the right to object to us using your personal information for the above purposes. If you wish to object to any of the above processing, please contact us on dataprotection@britishtriathlon.org.  If we agree and comply with your objection, this may affect our ability to use the API.
We also process your personal information in pursuit of our legitimate interests to:
monitor and develop the sport of Triathlon by monitoring engagement and participation through clubs, events and membership and inviting participants and users of ClubSpark to join British Triathlon, to participate in surveys for researching and development purposes;
Why we need your personal information - consent
We use consent as the legal basis to:
send out emails with updates concerning our ClubSpark APIs.
You are always able to remove your consent by clicking the unsubscribe link at the bottom of any email sent out or by contacting us at dataprotection@britishtriathlon.org.
Who we share your personal information with
Your data may be shared with data processors such as Mailchimp to help with our communication delivery.
How long we keep your personal information
Your email address will be retained until we no longer offer the ClubSpark system. Or until you ask us to remove it.
Transferral of personal data outside the European Union
Your personal data may be transferred outside of the EU when using third party services such as MailChimp which we use to help with our communications.
Whenever your data is transferred outside the EU we will make sure the organisation receiving the personal data has provided adequate safeguards.
Jump to the section on your rights and how to contact us.
Visitors to our websites
Analytics
We use a third party service, Google Analytics, to collect information to help us better understand how people use our website: for example which areas are being used more frequently than others and whether more people view the website on a mobile device rather than a desktop. This information is only processed in a way which does not identify anyone. We do not make, and do not allow Google to make, any attempt to find out the identities of those visiting our website.
Our legal basis for processing this information is legitimate interests.
The retention period for user-level and event-level data stored by Google Analytics is set at 26 months and the retention period is not reset on each new activity from a visitor.
Use of cookies
You can read more about how we use cookies on our Cookies page.
Security and performance
British Triathlon processes the IP addresses and user agents of visitors in certain areas to help maintain the security and performance of the British Triathlon website.
Our legal basis for processing this information is legitimate interests.
These are retained for at least one year but often much longer to allow for long-term reporting.
Jump to the section on your rights and how to contact us.
Annual Awards Nomination
If you nominate someone for a Triathlon England award, you will submit your information and that of the nominee in an application form (through Survey Monkey). Any personal information you provide, is only used only for the purpose of reviewing the nomination and, will be deleted after the award process has been completed. The name and case study of winners will also be published in media releases and on our own website.Other uses of your personal information
We may ask you if we can process your personal information for additional purposes. Where we do so, we will provide you with an additional privacy notice with information on how we will use your information for these additional purposes.
What information are we talking about?
Personal information is any information that makes you ‘You’ and can be used to identify you. Your name, email address and telephone number are all examples of personal information.
Why we need your personal information - legitimate interests
We process our members’ personal information in pursuit of our legitimate interests to:
Ensure that we are fair in relation to our processes for awards and prizes and to enable us to carry out our operations as a National Governing body of Triathlon and to fulfil our role in relation to the pursuit, encouragement and maintenance of excellence in Triathlon and to promote for public benefit.
Invite our members as award winners or guests to our awards ceremony which includes asking our clubs to nominate individuals for awards and shortlisting such individuals to select the winners, who we will then contact by email;
Deliver film and photography. Our awards process may be filmed for live streaming purposes and your personal information may also be used in images captured from the awards ceremony, which we use for promotional, education and development purposes;
Transfer of personal data outside the European Union
Your personal data may be transferred outside of the EU when using third party services such as Dropbox, MailChimp or SurveyMonkey. Whenever your data is transferred outside the EU, we will make sure the organisation receiving the personal data has provided adequate safeguards. For example, Dropbox and MailChimp participate in and has certified their compliance with the EU-U.S. Privacy Shield Framework and the Swiss-U.S Privacy Shield Framework.
Jump to the section on your rights and how to contact us.
Your rights
Under the Data Protection Act 1998 and General Data Protection Regulation, you have rights as an individual which you can exercise in relation to the information we hold about you. You can read more about these rights at https://ico.org.uk/for-the-public/is-my-information-being-handled-correctly/.
Your rights include:
your right to request access to the personal information that we hold about you by making a subject access request;
if you believe that any of your personal information is inaccurate or incomplete, you have a right to request that we correct or complete your personal information;
your right to request that we restrict the processing of your personal information for specific purposes; and
if you wish us to delete your personal information, you may request that we do so.
Access to personal information
British Triathlon tries to be as open as it can be in terms of giving people access to their personal information. Individuals can find out if we hold any personal information by making a ‘subject access request’. If we do hold information about you we can:
give you a description of it;
tell you why we are holding it;
tell you who it could be disclosed to; and
let you have a copy of the information in an intelligible form.
To make a request to British Triathlon for any personal information we may hold, please contact us on the contact details provided below or by emailing dataprotection@britishtriathlon.org.
If we do hold information about you, you can also ask us to correct any mistakes by contacting us or correcting it yourself within your My Account.
Complaints or queries
British Triathlon tries to meet the highest standards when collecting and using personal information. For this reason, we take any complaints we receive about this very seriously. We encourage people to bring it to our attention if they think that our collection or use of information is unfair, misleading or inappropriate. We would also welcome any suggestions for improving our procedures. Please contact us using the contact details provided further down this page.
You also have the right to lodge a complaint with a supervisory authority, which, in this instance, is the Information Commissioner's Office (ICO). If you want to make a complaint about the way we have processed your personal information, you should do so on the ICO website: https://www.ico.org.uk/concerns.
Links to other websites
This privacy notice does not cover the links within this site linking to other websites. We encourage you to read the privacy statements on the other websites you visit.
Changes to this privacy notice
We keep our privacy notice under regular review. This privacy notice was last updated on 3 August 2018.
How to contact us
If you want to request information about our privacy policy you can email us at dataprotection@britishtriathlon.org or write to:
Share this:
And enjoy insurance benefits, race licensing and more...
Join British Triathlon
